so these paradoxes that are kind of gas
and are newing paradoxes are an
indication that something about what we
think we know is off okay
that's why things appear to be
incompatible yeah the universe has to be
compatible everything and it simply does
exist and because everything in it
exists at the same time it all gets
along in some way so if some set of
facts doesn't seem to be able to be
reconciled that means that something
within the set of assumptions that we're
using to process them or the set of
facts that we think we know to be true
is actually not right when something
tells you that there is a missing piece
of knowledge most people's reaction to
that is darn I wish we weren't missing
knowledge but the right reaction if you
want to discover new things is well
here's one that we can detect is missing
we don't know what it is but if we could
figure out what it is who knows what
might flow from it the fact that we get
headaches tell us that something is
being reported to our brain but there's
no reason that anything should be
imported that doesn't have that doesn't
change your course of action in some way
that would have benefited an ancestor so
it is mysterious why we would have a
kind of pain that not only doesn't
inform us of something useful to do but
it debilitates us a headache we'll take
you out you might have something that
you could do that you can't do because
you can't do it while you got ahead so
that's hobbling that's obviously bad for
you from the point of view of
accomplishing whatever it is that you're
built to do so why would a system have
no useful output when you have a
headache you don't know what you're
supposed to do about it but nonetheless
debilitate us
that's a paradoxical thing and so my
contention is that in fact there is a
utility to the information that we get
from headaches and that it's a bit lost
in the modern firemen so let me go
through an example where pain works in a
normal fashion so if people can see what
we're trying to map
imagine the iconic situation where
you've touched something that's too hot
on the stove and you feel pain and it
causes you to withdraw your hand I would
draw in your hand you limit the amount
of damage that you do to the tissue of
your hand so the pain had a value in
that it reduced the amount of burning
the pain is a secondary value in the
sense that if you didn't pull your hand
away in time and you have actually
burned some tissue the pain will get you
to protect that tissue so it has a
chance but then it has a third value
which is it will cause you to learn that
things sitting on the stove may be more
dangerous than those objects for you to
see them sitting somewhere else and so
presumably you don't have to learn this
lesson each time but you start to
recognize the danger on the stove and
burn yourselves very much less
frequently and pain has served an
adaptive function in that laughing so my
contention with with headaches and in
particular with migraine headaches is
that they are an indicator of some sort
of internal measurement of damage so
imagine for example that an ancestor
maybe a hunter-gatherer that was part of
a migrant band moved at some point in
the year to a particular waterhole and
let's say that that source of water
tasted good enough because there was
nothing decaying in it that made it
dangerous and it was safe in that way
but maybe it has heavy metal
concentrations that result in cellular
damage when when you you drink enough of
it well if such damage triggered a
headache
an ancestor would be very likely to
detect the pattern that is to say at
every point in the year where the group
moves from one water source to another
headaches begin many people experience
them people who for whatever reason have
drunk from a different water source
might not get them and then when people
went away for a hunting trip the
headaches might vanish so there would be
pattern observable in the distribution
of headaches across the population and
and over time and that would very likely
be detectable it could be mediated
through something like cytokines which
are molecules that are internally
generated when certain kinds of stress
and damage are experienced but it
doesn't have to be the hypothesis is
simply that those headaches are an
indicator of some kind of harm that can
be mitigated if a person is driven to
modify their behavior so as not to
encounter the stimulus imagine though
that in our circumstance you're for
whatever reasons sensitive to broccoli
let's say that you have an allergy to
broccoli and that it is a trigger for
migraines for you well you might not
detect that because in our circumstance
even though broccoli grows you know in
the spring
broccoli is available year-round because
the supermarket sources it from other
places and make sure that you have it
have it available for cooking and so
what that means is that the patterns
that would be detectable to an ancestor
get lost in our circumstance in the
noise and there's no mechanism for
seeing them in general so one if one
wants to detect these patterns you have
to go through a very deliberate process
of keeping track of which foods you've
eaten on each day and then keeping track
when you have headaches and then seeing
where there's overlap between those two
but that's really a feature of the
complexity of modern life more than
anything else